Guide to the E. Dorrit Hoffleit Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
E. Dorrit Hoffleit papers
1847-2006
1945-2000
MS 1915
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.5
(9 boxes)
The materials consist primarily of research notes; materials for presentations and articles; correspondence; photographs; biographical materials, and printed ephemera documenting the career of E. Dorrit Hoffleit in the field of astronomy.
Hoffleit, Dorrit, 1907-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Astronomy Department, Yale University, 2008. Materials were removed from Hoffleit's office by the Astronomy Department following her death.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Ellen Dorrit Hoffleit was born in Florence, Alabama, on March 12, 1907. She received a B.A. in mathematics (1928) and a Ph.D. in astronomy (1938) from Radcliffe College; and a D.Sc. from Smith College (1984) and from Central Connecticut State University (1998). Hoffleit was a research assistant at the Harvard College Observatory in 1929 and was hired as an astronomer at Harvard in 1948. In 1943, she joined the Ballistic Research Laboratory at Aberdeen Proving Ground to compute missile trajectories. Hoffleit left Harvard in 1956 to run Yale University's star cataloging program. She authored the Bright Star Catalogue, containing information on the 9,110 brightest stars, and co-authored the General Catalogue of Trigonometric Stellar Parallaxes, containing precise distance measurements to 8,112 stars. She retired from Yale in 1975. Hoffleit was also director of the Maria Mitchell Observatory, Nantucket, from 1957 to 1978. In 1988, minor planet 3416 was named "Dorrit"in her honor. Hoffleit died at her New Haven, Connecticut, apartment on April 9, 2007.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist primarily of research notes; materials for presentations and articles; correspondence; photographs; biographical materials, and printed ephemera documenting the career of E. Dorrit Hoffleit in the field of astronomy.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as received from the Astronomy Department, Yale University.
Astrometry; Astronomers; Astronomy; Stars; Variable stars; Women astronomers; Hoffleit, Dorrit, 1907-
- Chronological files, Circa 1938-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1-22)
  Scope and Contents
  Files include correspondence, printed ephemera, clippings, and writings.
- Notebooks containing mostly bibliographic citations, Circa 1980-2000 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
- MACHO collaboration materials, Circa 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
- Bright Star Catalogue, research materials relating to publication, Circa 1950-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1-28)
- Mira, Christmas star, research materials, Circa 1980-2002 (Box 2, Folder 29-36)
- Research files on astronomers and astronomy, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 2, Folder 37-47)
  Includes photographs and biographical information, primarily about Yale and Harvard astronomers.
- Research files on astronomers, observatories, and telescopes, Circa 1900-2005
  Includes photographs, biographical information, correspondence, and drafts of writings, primarily about Yale and Harvard astronomers and women in astronomy.
  - Photographs, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Research files, photographs, Circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Small groups, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pictures Yale, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photograph-Conference on Spectroscopy, Circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs Mt. Stromlo, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous on Historic Topics, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pictures, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Yale Men, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Portraits of Male Astronomers, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Women Astronomers, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Telescopes, Research Notes, and Photographs, Circa 1900-1950 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Women, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Harvard Women as Astronomers to Compare with Yale, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Yale, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Yale Observatory History, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Women Astronomers at Yale Through 1968, Circa 1900-1968 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Research materials on astronomers and observatories, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Research materials on astronomers and observatories, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Yale Telescopes, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Women, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Margaretta Palmer, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Shapley I, 1928-1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Shapley II, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Harvard Women Professionals in Science and Engineering, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Women scientists, Circa 1990-2005 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - MMA - Women in Science Award, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Pertaining to Helen Lewis Thomas, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Women in Astronomy Lecture, January 27, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Women Astronomers, 1989-2004 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Transparencies: Women Astronomers, Circa 1900-2005 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Observatories, non-Yale, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Photographs not relating to historical research, Circa 1920-1980
  Includes primarily family and professional photographs.
  - Photographs, early, Circa 1920-1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Photographs, early family, Circa 1920-1980 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Photographs, early, some family, Circa 1920-1980 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Haley's comet research materials, slides, photographs, and correspondence, Circa 1980-1989
  - Halley's Comet - History and Predictions, Circa 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Halley's Comet slides, Circa 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- First star photography, photographs, pamphlets, notes, and writings for an exhibit, 1847-circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Ballistic Research Laboratories (Aberdeen, Maryland), correspondence, photographs, and research materials, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
- Al Sufi variations, 1943-circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
- Beehler, Christmas star, Circa 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Berendzen, loan of images, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- On the identification of CF Sct, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Review of McIvor, Star of Bethlehem, Star of Messiah, Circa 1998 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- "Fleming, Maury, Cannon, and the Classification of Stars," lecture materials, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
- Comet catalogue, Circa 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Illustrated Guide to Astronomy illustrations, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Comet Charles V, Circa 1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Meteors and meteorites, Circa 1950-2000 (Box 4, Folder 16-24)
- Research notes, Circa 1950-2000 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Long-period variables, for New Zealand colloquium, Circa 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Notes from Perth conference, Circa 1960-1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Pulsar pair, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Sydney plates and plate replacement, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Transit of Venus, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- "More Observations Needed for V370 and, An Hipparcos Discovery", 1998 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Variable star transparency, Circa 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 31-33)
- Vassar College centennial, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Costantino, Sigismondi, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Interview of astronomer Dr. Dorrit Hoffleit by Dr. Pan Papacosta, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  Contains correspondence and transcript of interview.
  General
  See also: Recording of interview, 2003 January 29
  - Recording of interview, 2003 January 29; 2008-m-079-001; 1 (Box 6U)
- Lecture transparencies, Circa 1950-2000 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Non-Mira variables, Circa 1980-2000 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- American Association of Variable Star Observers (AAVSO), Circa 1960-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
- Lecture transparencies, Circa 1950-2000 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
- Research materials, 1910-1994 (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
- "History of the Discovery of Mira-type Stars", Circa 1970-1990 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Janet Mattei memorial, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Frank Schlesinger, lecture materials, Circa 1970-1990 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Astronomical telescopes, Circa 1936-1980 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Catalogue cameras, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- 90th Anni Mirabiles, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- "Pioneering Women in Spectral Classification of Stars", 2002 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Helen Lewis Thomas, Circa 1997 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Research notes and transparencies, Circa 1970-1990 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Meteorites, research materials, 1945-2000 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences talk on Meteoritics, Circa 1998 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Notes for a talk on the history of astronomy, Circa 1950-1970 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Non-Mira red giants, lecture materials, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Suspected variables among Al Sufi stars, lecture materials, Circa 1990-2000 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Sydney Barnes AAVSO paper, lecture materials, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Spectra, Circa 1970-2000 (Box 5, Folder 30-33)
- Spectroscopy, Circa 1970-2000 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Connecticut Women's Hall of Fame, induction materials, 1998-2000 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Asteroids, Circa 1985-1995 (Box 5, Folder 36-38)
- Astrometry, 1969-1989 (Box 5, Folder 39-40)
- Astronomers as musicians, essay drafts and research materials, Circa 1938-2000 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
- Family and friends, correspondence, 1997-2003 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Daguerreotype of Jupiter, facsimiles of materials apparently from the George Eastman House, Rochester, New York, Circa 1850 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Satellites and Russian space exploration, research notes, clippings, and printed ephemera, 1957-1961 (Box 7, Folder 6-8)
- Brouwer (Dirk) medal, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Camera lens, Argentina, includes photographs, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Yale astronomy, research notes, clippings, and correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Yale zone catalogue, errata and other information, Circa 1950-1985 (Box 7, Folder 12-24)
- Radcliffe College and biographical files, Circa 1928-2002 (Box 7, Folder 25-32)
  Includes correspondence, essays, clippings, and research materials.
  - Citations and posters celebrating Hoffleit's achievements, 1997-2006 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Chronology relating to astronomy and New Haven/Yale, Circa 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 33)
- "The Harvard Observatory Development" typescript, Circa 1940-1950 (Box 7, Folder 34)
- Notes on the history of science and the Yale Observatory, Circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 35)
- Astronomy research notes and figures, Circa 1975-1985 (Box 7, Folder 36-37)
- Bibliographical and biographical information, Circa 1980-1993 (Box 7, Folder 38-39)
- Notes from annual reports, Circa 1920-1966 (Box 7, Folder 40)
- The Athenaeum, Yale's first observatory, research notes, Circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 41)
- Eclipses other than 1925, notes, Circa 1970-1990 (Box 7, Folder 42)
- Astronomical Society of the Pacific correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 43)
- Transit of Venus, essay, notes, and correspondence, 1942-2004 (Box 7, Folder 44-45)
- Meteoric astronomy, notes and drafts for article in Garland Encyclopedia, Circa 1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Lawrence Summers controversy at Harvard, clippings and correspondence, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- "Astronomy with the Yale heliometer, 1882-1910" drafts and research materials, Circa 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Variable stars, notes, Circa 1970-1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- History of Yale observatory, overheads for colloquium talk, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Humor, mostly clippings, Circa 1980-2000 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Astronomy teaching materials, Circa 1985-1995 (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
- Minneapolis balloon flight data, 1956 April (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Observatory photographs for Sydney paper, Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
- William Augustus Norton, biographical and bibliographical information, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Obituaries, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Observatories, articles on, 1963-1995 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Witwatersrand University (South Africa) and Yale telescope, correspondence and photographs, 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Stellar parallaxes, drafts, correspondence, and printed ephemera, Circa 1945-1970 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Peabody Museum instruments, memoranda and notes, 1992-1995 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Photography of stars, research materials, 1981-1989 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Photometry, research materials, Circa 1980-1990 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Radio astronomy, research materials, Circa 1960-1990 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- References, call numbers, Circa 1960-1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- SIMBAD database instructional and research materials, Circa 1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- J. Lawrence Smith fund and National Academy of Sciences correspondence and printed ephemera, Circa 1921-1987 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Astonomical Society of the Pacific Toronto meeting materials, Circa 1999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Telescopes research notes, Circa 1900-1990 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Yale-United States Naval Observatory cooperation research materials and drafts, Circa 1960-2000 (Box 9, Folder 6-8)
- Wellesley College Class of 1959 printed ephemera (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Yale-Loomis telescope installation instructions and visual materials, Circa 1942 (Box 9, Folder 10)